Hale Family Papers, 1787-1988
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- HALE FAMILY
  - Generation II
    - Hale, Sarah Preston Everett (1796-1866) [Mrs. Nathan, Sr.]
      - Correspondence, outgoing
        - Hale, Enoch and Octavia (Throop) [parents-in-law], 1831, 1833 (Box 13, Folder 20)
        - Hale, Lucretia Peabody [daughter], 1839(?)-66 (Box 13, Folder 21-22)
        - Hale, Nathan, Sr. [husband]
          - 1816-49 (Box 13, Folder 23-25)
          - 1850-54 (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
        - Hale, Nathan, Jr. [son], 1837-64 (Box 14, Folder 4-7)
        - Hale, Sarah Everett [daughter], 1838-51 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
        - Hale, Susan [daughter], 1844-66 (Box 14, Folder 10)
        - Miscellaneous, 1850-65, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, incoming, 1826-51, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Writings
        - Correspondence with publishers, 1829-46 (Box 15, Folder 3)
        - Diaries, Jun 1850, 1859-62 (Box 15, Folder 5-9)
        - Royalty statements, 1883-98 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Hale, Richard (1792-1839)
      - Correspondence
        - Hale, Enoch, Jr. [brother], 1837 (Box 15, Folder 11)
        - Hale, Nathan, Sr. [brother], 1814-39 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Hall, Sybella (Hale) (1797-?): letters to Enoch Hale, Sr. [father], 1817 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Hooker, Octavia (Hale) (1788-?): letters to Hale, Jane (Murdock) [sister-in-law], 1833 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - McCall, Melissa (Hale) (1786-?)
      - Correspondence, outgoing
        - Hale, Enoch, Jr. and Jane (Murdock) [brother and sister-in-law], 1846 (Box 15, Folder 15)
        - Hale, Nathan, Sr. and Sarah Preston (Everett), [brother and sister-in-law] 1829-52 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Generation III
    - Hale, Alexander (1829-1850) "Elly"
      - General, 1850 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, outgoing
        - Hale, Charles [brother], 1846(?)-49(?) (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Hale, Edward Everett [brother], 1843-50(?) (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Hale, Lucretia Peabody [sister], 1839-50 (Box 16, Folder 4)
        - Hale, Nathan, Jr. [brother], 1838, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
        - Hale, Sarah Everett [sister], 1848-50 (Box 16, Folder 6)
        - Hale, Sarah Preston (Everett) [mother], 1844-50 (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
        - Hale, Susan [sister], 1848-50 (Box 16, Folder 9)
        - Fragment, circa 1846 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Diary, travel, 1848 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Hale, Charles (1831-1882)
      - Biographical materials and memorabilia
        - General, 1840, 1859, 1880(?), 1967 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - Artwork, 1897, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
        - "The History of Mr. Seward's Pet in Egypt" by Francis Dainese, 1866 (Box 17, Folder 3)
        - Keene (NH) Invalid's Home, 1873-75 (Box 17, Folder 4)
        - Notebook, 1853 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Activities
        - Boston Weekly Messenger
          - Correspondence, 1853-76, undated (Box 17, Folder 6-12)
          - Financial and legal, 1854, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
        - Harvard University, 1855-76 (Box 17, Folder 14)
        - Massachusetts government
          - Correspondence, 1855-76, undated (Box 17, Folder 15-16)
          - Election party tickets, 1874, undated (Box 17, Folder 17)
          - Railroad Commissioner, 1871-76 (Box 17, Folder 18)
        - Today: A Boston Literary Journal, 1852 (Box 17, Folder 19)
        - U. S. Department of State
          - Assistant Secretary, 1872-74 (Box 17, Folder 20-21)
          - General Consul to Egypt, 1864-68 (Box 17, Folder 22)
      - Correspondence, outgoing
        - Everett, Edward [uncle], 1856-59 (Box 18, Folder 1)
        - Everett, William [cousin], 1863-74 (Box 18, Folder 2)
        - Hale groups, 1851-71 (Box 18, Folder 3-4)
        - Hale, Alexander "Elly" [brother], 1849-50 (Box 18, Folder 5)
        - Hale, Edward Everett [brother]
          - 1849-61 (Box 18, Folder 6-29)
          - 1862-Mar1872 (Box 19, Folder 1-46)
          - Apr 1872-1880(?) (Box 20, Folder 1-10)
        - Hale, Lucretia Peabody [sister], 1839, 1850-80 (Box 20, Folder 11-22)
        - Hale, Nathan, Jr. [brother], 1850-69 (Box 20, Folder 23-25)
        - Hale, Nathan, Sr. [father], 1850-60 (Box 20, Folder 26-27)
        - Hale, Sarah Everett [sister], 1850 (Box 20, Folder 28)
        - Hale, Sarah Preston (Everett) [mother]
          - 1846-51 (Box 20, Folder 29-32)
          - 1852-Oct 1861 (Box 21, Folder 1-33)
          - Nov 1861-Mar 1866 (Box 22, Folder 1-38)
          - Apr-Dec 1866 (Box 23, Folder 1-11)
        - Hale, Susan [sister]
          - 1849-Nov 1868 (Box 23, Folder 12-19)
          - Dec 1868-1878 (Box 24, Folder 1-6)
        - Fragments of letters to Hales, undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
        - Miscellaneous, 1851-80 (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, incoming
        - Bancroft, George, 1869, 1876 (Box 24, Folder 9)
        - Denny, Henry G., 1865 (Box 24, Folder 10)
        - Howells, William Dean, 1862-65 (Box 24, Folder 11)
          [See also Activities, Boston Weekly Messenger and Writings, Correspondence]
        - Thayer, William Sydney, 1855 (Box 24, Folder 12)
        - Miscellaneous, A-Z, 1855-76, undated (Box 24, Folder 13)
      - Writings
        - Correspondence, 1872-76 (Box 24, Folder 14)
        - Notes, circa 1861 (Box 24, Folder 15)
        - Manuscripts, 1861-62 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - Hale, Edward Everett (1822-1909) and Emily (Perkins) (1829-1914) Household
      - Baby book, 1860-71 (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1873, 1882 (Box 25, Folder 2)
      - Financial
        - General, 1871, 1891 (Box 25, Folder 3)
        - Ledgers, 1866-67, 1869-84 (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
      - Household bills, trade cards, 1904-13, undated (Box 25, Folder 6)
      - Houses: deeds, mortgages, etc., 1852-1912, undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
      - The Meteor (family newspaper), 1868-69 (Box 25, Folder 8)
      - Notebook with questionnaire re: tastes, 1861 (Box 25, Folder 9)
      - Paper dolls and soldiers, undated (Box 25, Folder 10)
      - Play "William Tell: A Drama in Four Acts After Schiller" by E. and E. and A., 1870 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Postmark collection (Herbert Dudley, Philip Leslie, and Robert Beverly Hale),1870s-80s (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Wedding anniversary, 50th: correspondence, 1902 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Charlieshope Library homemade books by Ellen Day and Arthur Hale and friends (57 volumes), 1865-68, undated (Box 26)
        [See Appendix II for title list]
    - Hale, Edward Everett (1822-1909)
      - Biographical materials and memorabilia
        - General, 1896-1965, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
        - Artwork, 1851, undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
        - Biographies, 1915-17 (Box 27, Folder 3)
        - Birthdays
          - 64th, 1886 (Box 27, Folder 4)
          - 70th, 1892
            - Letters and tributes, A-Z (Box 27, Folder 5-7)
            - Banquet: program, invitations, and arrangements (Box 27, Folder 8)
            - Publication
              - Correspondence and drafts (Box 27, Folder 9)
              - Manuscript (Box 27, Folder 10)
            - Clippings (Box 28, Folder 1)
            - Tribute books (Box 28, Folder 2-5)
          - 75th, 1897: correspondence (Box 28, Folder 6)
          - 80th, 1902
            - Programs, invitation, and arrangements (Box 28, Folder 7)
            - Clippings (Box 29, Folder 1)
            - Letters and tributes, A-Z (Box 29, Folder 2-7)
            - Letters from school children (Box 29, Folder 8)
        - Death, 1909
          - Clippings (Box 29, Folder 9)
          - Condolence letters
            - A-S (Box 29, Folder 10-17)
            - T-Z and unidentified (Box 30, Folder 1)
          - Fiftieth anniversary commemoration service, 1959 (Box 30, Folder 2)
        - Estate, 1909-10 (Box 30, Folder 3)
        - Memorabilia, 1829-1909, undated (Box 30, Folder 4-5)
        - New York University Hall of Fame nomination, 1920 (Box 30, Folder 6)
        - Retirement, 1899 (Box 30, Folder 7)
        - Statue by Bela L. Pratt, Boston Public Garden, 1913-42, undated (Box 30, Folder 8)
      - Activities
        - Scrapbooks
          [See indexes at end of each volume]
          - circa 1845-81 (Box 31)
          - circa 1852-79 (Box 32)
        - General, 1860-78 (Box 33, Folder 1)
        - Anti-slavery/Freedman's Aid, 1862-71, undated (Box 33, Folder 2)
        - Boston, City of, 1863-89, undated (Box 33, Folder 3)
        - Boston Weekly Messenger, sale of, 1854 (Box 33, Folder 4)
        - Boston Public Library, 1865, 1885 (Box 33, Folder 5)
        - Boston Young Men's Christian Union, 1859-78 (Box 33, Folder 6)
        - Boys Institute of Industry, 1909, undated (Box 33, Folder 7)
        - Civil War and Reconstruction, 1863-65, undated (Box 33, Folder 8)
        - Clubs, 1850?-89, undated (Box 33, Folder 9)
        - Emigrant Aid, 1861-65, undated (Box 33, Folder 10)
        - Historical Associations
          - General, 1862-84, undated (Box 33, Folder 11)
          - Massachusetts Historical Society, 1861-65 (Box 33, Folder 12)
        - Hospitals, 1865, 1978, undated (Box 33, Folder 13)
        - Investment opportunities, 1863-75, undated (Box 33, Folder 14)
        - Lend a Hand Society
          - General, 1888-1965, undated (Box 33, Folder 15)
          - Publications
            - General, 1897-1906, undated (Box 33, Folder 16)
            - Circulars of Ten Times One is Ten, Vol. I and II, 1885 (Box 33, Folder 17)
        - New England Refugees' Aid Society, 1865, undated (Box 33, Folder 18)
        - Old and New, 1870-74, undated (Box 33, Folder 19)
        - Periodicals, 1864-76, undated (Box 33, Folder 20)
        - Poor relief
          - General, 1858-77, undated (Box 33, Folder 21)
          - North Street Mission for the Poor, 1861-64 (Box 33, Folder 22)
        - Prisons, 1859, 1865, undated (Box 33, Folder 23)
        - Religious
          - General, 1858-78, undated (Box 33, Folder 24)
          - Society for Encouraging Religious Education, 1880 (Box 33, Folder 25)
          - South Congregational Church, 1804-78 (Box 33, Folder 26)
          - Unitarian Church
            - General, 1859-1909, undated (Box 33, Folder 27)
            - American Unitarian Association, 1858-1909, undated (Box 33, Folder 28)
        - Schools and colleges
          - General, 1829-72, undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
          - Antioch College, 1865-67, undated (Box 34, Folder 2)
          - Hampton Normal and Industrial Institute, 1868-78 (Box 34, Folder 3)
          - Harvard College, 1850-1939, undated (Box 34, Folder 4)
        - Temperance, 1865, undated (Box 34, Folder 5)
        - United States Sanitary Commission, 1861-65 (Box 34, Folder 6)
        - United States Senate Chaplaincy, 1905, undated (Box 34, Folder 7)
        - Women's Education Association, 1877, undated (Box 34, Folder 8)
        - Women's Rest Tour Association, undated (Box 34, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, outgoing
        - Arnold, Helen (Freeman) undated (Box 34, Folder 10)
        - Freeman, Helen Elizabeth, 1884-1906 (Box 34, Folder 10a)
        - Freeman, Harriet Clark, Helen Hunt, and Caroline, 1897-1908 (Box 34, Folder 11)
        - Hale groups, 1896-1908 (Box 34, Folder 12)
        - Hale siblings, 1877-99 (Box 34, Folder 13)
        - Hale children groups, 1866-95, 1902 (Box 34, Folder 14)
        - Hale, Ellen Day [daughter]
          - 1859-1901 (Box 34, Folder 15-30)
          - 1902-09, undated (Box 35, Folder 1-3)
        - Hale, Emily (Perkins) [wife], 1873-1909, undated (Box 35, Folder 4-5)
        - Hale, Enoch [father], 1858-61 (Box 35, Folder 5A)
        - Hale, Philip Leslie and Lilian (Westcott) [son and daughter-in-law], 1902-09, undated (Box 35, Folder 6)
        - Hale, Nancy [granddaughter], 1909 (Box 35, Folder 7)
        - Hale, Sarah Preston (Everett) [mother], 1856 (Box 35, Folder 8)
        - Whitman, Minnie (Hamilton), 1859-1907, undated (Box 35, Folder 9-11)
        - Non-family, misc., 1852-1910 (Box 35, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, incoming
        - A, 1855-95 (Box 35, Folder 13)
        - Addams, Jane, 1893 (Box 35, Folder 14)
        - Agassiz, Elizabeth Carey and Louis R., 1852, 1874 (Box 35, Folder 15)
        - Alcott, Louisa May, 1863 (Box 35, Folder 16)
        - Alger, Horatio, Jr., 1861 (Box 35, Folder 17)
        - Antin, Mary, 1900 (Box 35, Folder 18)
        - Armstrong, S.C., 1886, 1888, undated (Box 35, Folder 19)
        - Atherton, Gertrude, 1904 (Box 35, Folder 20)
        - B, 1855-1904, undated (Box 35, Folder 21)
        - Bancroft, George, 1858-70 (Box 35, Folder 22)
        - Barrows, S.J., 1876, 1884 (Box 35, Folder 23)
        - Beecher, Henry Ward, 1881 (Box 35, Folder 24)
        - Bell, Alexander Graham, 1872, 1894 (Box 35, Folder 25)
        - Bigelow, John, 1888 (Box 35, Folder 26)
        - Butler, Benjamin Franklin, 1868 (Box 35, Folder 27)
        - Bynner, Edwin L., 1876-87 (Box 35, Folder 28)
        - C, 1846-1907, undated (Box 35, Folder 29)
        - Cable, George Washington, 1888-99 (Box 35, Folder 30)
        - Choate, Joseph H., 1876-91 (Box 35, Folder 31)
        - Church, Frederick, 1893 (Box 35, Folder 32)
        - Cooper, Susan Fenimore, 1887 (Box 35, Folder 33)
        - Cushing, Frank Hamilton, 1899 (Box 35, Folder 34)
        - D, 1837-1904, undated (Box 35, Folder 35)
        - E, 1857-95 (Box 35, Folder 36)
        - Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1859, undated (Box 35, Folder 37)
        - F, 1847-1904, undated (Box 35, Folder 38)
        - Fields, Annie, 1887-91, undated (Box 35, Folder 39)
        - Freeman, Helen Hunt, undated (Box 35, Folder 40)
        - G, 1866-1907, undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
        - Gaskell, Elizabeth, Meta, Mariam, and William, 1860-62 (Box 36, Folder 2)
        - Gilder, Joseph B., Jeannette L., and R.W., 1875-97 (Box 36, Folder 3)
        - Grant, Robert, 1874, undated (Box 36, Folder 4)
        - Gray, Asa, 1854-87, undated (Box 36, Folder 5)
        - Greenough, Richard, 1844-72 (Box 36, Folder 6)
        - Greenwood, Grace (Mrs. Lippincott), 1894 (Box 36, Folder 7)
        - H, 1854-1901, undated (Box 36, Folder 8)
        - Hall, G. Stanley, 1878-90, undated (Box 36, Folder 9)
        - Hamlin, Cyrus, 1890-96 (Box 36, Folder 10)
        - Hawley, Joseph R., 1865, 1890 (Box 36, Folder 11)
        - Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1854-1901, undated (Box 36, Folder 12)
        - Hoar, George F., 1851-1904 (Box 36, Folder 13)
        - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1887, undated (Box 36, Folder 14)
        - Howe, Julia Ward, 1871-88, undated (Box 36, Folder 15)
        - Howells, William Dean, 1864-1908 (Box 36, Folder 16)
        - I-J, 1870-98 (Box 36, Folder 17)
        - Jewett, Sarah Orne, 1871, undated (Box 36, Folder 18)
        - K, 1873, 1888 (Box 36, Folder 19)
        - L, 1867-97, undated (Box 36, Folder 20)
        - Lincoln, Robert Todd, 1883-99 (Box 36, Folder 21)
        - Livermore, Mary, 1888-92 (Box 36, Folder 22)
        - Long, John D., 1894-1902 (Box 36, Folder 23)
        - Loomis, Charles Battell, 1900-01 (Box 36, Folder 24)
        - M, 1856-1900 (Box 36, Folder 25)
        - May, Samuel, 1851 (Box 36, Folder 26)
        - Miner, Myrtilla, 1858 (Box 36, Folder 27)
        - Mitchell, Maria, 1874 (Box 36, Folder 28)
        - N-O, 1873-1903 (Box 36, Folder 29)
        - Norton, Charles Eliot, 1877-1903 (Box 36, Folder 30)
        - Olmsted, Frederick Law, 1857, 1889 (Box 36, Folder 31)
        - Owen, Robert Dale, 1870 (Box 36, Folder 32)
        - P, 1855-1904, undated (Box 36, Folder 33)
        - Palfrey (?), John G., 1846-61 (Box 36, Folder 34)
        - Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1898 (Box 36, Folder 35)
        - Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer, 1856, undated (Box 36, Folder 36)
        - Phillips, Wendell, undated (Box 36, Folder 37)
        - Q-R, 1857-93, undated (Box 36, Folder 38)
        - Quincy, Josiah, 1874-75 (Box 36, Folder 39)
        - Riggs, Kate Douglas Wiggin, undated (Box 36, Folder 40)
        - Rockefeller, John D., 1897 (Box 36, Folder 41)
        - S, 1856-91 (Box 36, Folder 42)
        - Sanborn, F.B., 1870-75 (Box 36, Folder 43)
        - Scudder, Horace E., 1862-1900 (Box 36, Folder 44)
        - Stone, Lucy, 1889, 1890 (Box 36, Folder 45)
        - Sullivan, Annie M., 1888 (Box 36, Folder 46)
        - T, 1874-99, undated (Box 36, Folder 47)
        - Tarbell, Ida, 1896-1904 (Box 36, Folder 48)
        - V-Z, 1867-1902, undated (Box 36, Folder 49)
        - Ward, Elizabeth Stuart Phelps, 1889 (Box 36, Folder 50)
        - Washington, Booker T., 1886-1902 (Box 36, Folder 51)
        - Whitney, Adeline D. T., 1870-71 (Box 36, Folder 52)
        - Williams, Eleazer, 1852-57 (Box 36, Folder 53)
        - Winthrop, Robert C., 1872-94 (Box 36, Folder 54)
      - Correspondence, third party
        - Freeman, Harriet to Helen (Freeman) and Harold Arnold 1909-1912 (Box 36, Folder 55)
      - Speeches and writings
        - Addresses
          - Miscellaneous, 1879-1902 (Box 37, Folder 1)
          - Bicentennial of the First Parish in Framingham, 13 Oct 1901 (Box 37, Folder 2)
          - Dedication of the sixth meeting house, First Parish in Dorchester, 16 May 1897 (Box 37, Folder 3)
          - Funeral of Isaac Fenno, 28 Jun 1897 (Box 37, Folder 4)
          - Inauguration of John Gordon as President of Howard University, 30 Mar 1904 (Box 37, Folder 5)
          - Opening of the Rowland G. Hazard Memorial, Peace Dale, RI, 9 Oct 1891 (Box 37, Folder 6)
          - Service in memory of Phillips Brooks, 30 Jan 1894 (Box 37, Folder 7)
          - "Communion Service," 25 Nov 1906 (Box 37, Folder 8)
          - "The Contribution of Boston to American Independence," 121st celebration of the Declaration of Independence, Boston, 5 Jul 1897 (Box 37, Folder 9)
          - "The Educated Citizen," Smith College Commencement, 17 Jun 1902 (Box 37, Folder 10)
          - "The Five Great Duties of the Twentieth Century," University of Ohio Commencement, 19 Jun 1901 (Box 37, Folder 11)
          - "The Gospel of Emerson for His Time and Ours," Emerson Celebration, Boston, 31 Jul 1903 (Box 37, Folder 12)
          - "The Ideas of the Founders," Brooklyn Institute, 4 Nov 1903 (Box 37, Folder 13)
          - "The Leaders Lead," Alpha Delta Phi Convention, Williams College, 24 May 1877 (Box 37, Folder 14)
          - "Physical, Mental, and Spiritual Exercises," Philips Exeter Academy, Exeter, NH, 29 Sep 1885 (Box 37, Folder 15)
          - "Public Amusement for Poor and Rich," Church of the Unity, Worcester, MA, 16 Dec 1855 (Box 37, Folder 16)
          - "The Results of Columbus's Discovery," American Antiquarian Society, Worcester, MA, 21 Oct 1892 (Box 37, Folder 17)
          - "Thomas Starr King: A Memorial Address," South Congregational Church, Boston, MA, 1 Mar 1903 (Box 37, Folder 18)
          - "What is the American People?" Phi Beta Kappa Society, Brown University, Providence, RI, 1885 (Box 37, Folder 19)
          - "What Will He Do With It?" Cornell University Commencement, 12 Jun 1881 (Box 37, Folder 20)
        - Sermons by title
          - A-F (Box 37, Folder 21-22)
          - G-Z (Box 38, Folder 1-7)
        - Writings
          - Miscellaneous magazine and newspaper articles, 1879-1969, undated (Box 39, Folder 1)
          - "A Sunday Morning Prayer," undated (Box 39, Folder 2)
          - "Afloat and Ashore," 1891 (Box 39, Folder 3)
          - "Christmas Waits in Boston," circa 1859 (Box 39, Folder 4)
          - "Daily Bread: A Story of the Snow Blockade," 1888 (Box 39, Folder 5)
          - "Dr. Geo. E. Ellis": typescript, undated (Box 39, Folder 6)
          - "Gosnold at Cuttyhunk," 1902 (Box 39, Folder 7)
          - "The Great Harvest Year," undated (Box 39, Folder 8)
          - "Homer and David": dramatization of EEH story by Katherine E. Dopp, 1903 (Box 39, Folder 9)
          - "How They Live in Boston and How They Die There," undated (Box 39, Folder 10)
          - "How To Grow Young," 1911 (Box 39, Folder 11)
          - Introduction to a book by Miss Allen: ms., circa 1900 (Box 39, Folder 12)
          - "John Albion Andrew": typescript, undated (Box 39, Folder 13)
          - "The Maltese Cross": manuscript, undated ("printed and presented by the King's Daughters of Wellesley College, 1890") (Box 39, Folder 14)
          - "The Man Without a Country" 1863
            - Lend a Hand Society reprint, 1904 (Box 39, Folder 15)
            - Correspondence re: reprint in Outlook, 1889 (Box 39, Folder 16)
            - Dramatizations: correspondence, programs, and clippings, 1884-1937 (Box 39, Folder 17)
            - Film rights controversy: correspondence, 1917 (Box 39, Folder 18)
          - "Mrs. De Laix's Indecision": ms., undated (Box 39, Folder 19)
          - "My Grandmother's Mutton: A Boston Christmas Story": ms., undated (Box 39, Folder 20)
          - "Neither Scrip nor Money: A Christmas Story," circa 1903 (Box 39, Folder 21)
          - "Nel Suo Nome. Racconto dei Valdesi," 1887 (Box 39, Folder 22)
          - "Old Age Pensions," undated (Box 39, Folder 23)
          - "One Hundred Years Ago. How the War Began," 1875 (Box 39, Folder 24)
          - "Other Senators": typescript, undated (Box 39, Folder 25)
          - "The Professor of America": ms., undated (Box 39, Folder 26)
          - "Red and White. A Christmas Story," 1887 (Box 39, Folder 27)
          - "The Real Philip Nolan," 1901
            - Mississippi Historical Society Publications reprint (Box 39, Folder 28)
            - Research materials (Box 39, Folder 29-30)
            - Research materials (cont'd) (Box 40, Folder 1-8)
          - "Six Distinguished Men of Letters": typescript, undated
            - "Wendell Phillips" (Box 40, Folder 9)
            - "Daniel Webster" (Box 40, Folder 10)
            - "Ralph Waldo Emerson" (Box 40, Folder 11)
            - "Henry Wadsworth Longfellow" (Box 40, Folder 12)
            - "Josiah Quincy" (Box 40, Folder 13)
            - "John Quincy Adams" (Box 40, Folder 14)
          - "The Story of a Dory," undated (Box 40, Folder 15)
          - The Story of Massachusetts: pamphlet "To the Critics of the Story of Massachusetts," circa 1892 (Box 40, Folder 16)
          - "Studies in American Colonial Life," 1895 (Box 40, Folder 17)
          - "Susan's Escort"
            - Early draft: ms., undated (Box 40, Folder 18)
            - Later draft: ms., undated (Box 40, Folder 19)
          - That Unknown Country: reprint of Chapter XXI, undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
          - "Tom Torrey's Tariff Talks"
            - Reprint, 1888 (Box 41, Folder 2)
            - Manuscript
              - "The Cooking Stove" (Box 41, Folder 3)
              - "Well Enough Alone" (Box 41, Folder 4)
              - "The Jack Knife" (Box 41, Folder 5)
            - "Uncle Frank's Family and the Story He Told Them One New Year's Night," 1857 (Box 41, Folder 6)
            - "The Unitarian Principles," undated (Box 41, Folder 7)
            - "The Unknown Life of Jesus Christ," undated (Box 41, Folder 8)
          - Notes
            - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 41, Folder 9)
            - On Boston, undated (Box 41, Folder 10)
            - Folio "Parts of Translations, Sermons, and Christian History Lectures, 1846-1854. Epistles- Communion Address(?)" (Box 41, Folder 11-18)
            - Unitarian Communion Service (in Samuel Longfellow's hand) (Box 41, Folder 19)
          - Business/financial materials
            - Miscellaneous publishers, 1873-1906 (Box 42, Folder 1)
            - A.S. Barnes and Co., 1886-90 (Box 42, Folder 2)
            - American Book Co., 1891-1904 (Box 42, Folder 3)
            - Atlantic Monthly, 1882-97 (Box 42, Folder 4)
            - Cassell Publishing Co., 1891-1904 (Box 42, Folder 5-6)
            - The Century Co., 1907-09 (Box 42, Folder 7)
            - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1881-98 (Box 42, Folder 8)
            - D. Appleton and Co., 1897-98, undated (Box 42, Folder 9)